Hi friends, I'm Scott Hanselman, I wish I could be
there with you celebrating .NET and .NET conf in Japan.
But I'm here in Portland in my house.
This is my office, but I thought I would make
you a video to talk about .NET talk about .NET core how exciting it is
how important is how fun it is that it is
cross platform and I figured that you would like some
demos.
Some low level demos, so let's share my screen and
see some interesting .NET demos right now.
All right now, I said,
I would show lots of demos and I'm going to
try to spend most of my time at the command
line because I want you to understand what's inside .NET but
at the same time, it's really important to point out
and to keep emphasizing that it's your platform for building
anything,
the whole point, about .NET in.
2019. And in 2020, is you can build anything with
it.
In the past in the past.
Dot net was a windows thing.
You would install it on windows,
sometimes windows, wouldn't have .NET installed and you have to install dot
net 1st and then.
Install your app. We want net to be something that
you can build anything for you,
if you want to try to watch app.
You should do it in dot net if you want
to write an app for a Raspberry Pi.
You can do it in dot net if you want
to write an app for a video game or Xbox.
Nintendo switch C Sharp unity do it in .NET we wanna mobile app Android.
IPhone whatever makes you happy you want to write machine
learning code you can do it in .NET.
You can build anything, it's not just dot NET Framework
on Windows anymore .NET core is fully open source it runs
anywhere.
Dot, Net Core 3. Is a great version to start
on if you haven't been doing net lately or if
you've been doing net primarily with NET Framework.
4.7 or 4.8. Dot, Net Core 3 is a good
time to move forward also explain that in a little
bit.
I also want to point out that it's really,
really exciting that the community is getting involved.
There's a lot of community pull requests.
It's all on GitHub. It's entirely open source.
Even now in 2019 people still get confused and bosses
and companies and suits still don't get that dot net
is open source and not a little bit open source
completely open source on GitHub,
the compilers open source the runtime is open.
There's all the way down to the metal.
OK.
It's a good thing now.
It is released on at Core 3.0 is released,
you can go to dot dot net that's dot net.
You can go and get dot net core 3.
Now it includes support for Windows forms and WPF.
Those are windows. Things that can be a little bit
confusing.
I'm going to talk about that.
It also supports what's called side by side and self
contained exes.
I'm going to show you that again will spend time
looking at code at the command line.
It's also important to point out that not only .NET core
3 released,
but with it. C# 8. C#
8, is also released C# 8,
is the newest version of C#.
It is out and you get all these great new
language features with C# 8 in dot net core 3.0 and then
we also have blazer that will talk about a little
bit.
C# is just wonderful I'm not going to spend
too much time talking about it here.
But I just want you to associate that new version
of C# is out today as well,
which is really, really cool.
Now let's step away from slides slides are fun.
But we really want to do some stuff.
At the command line now this is my screen here
and I'm going to go and run the new Windows
terminal.
I'm just using the windows terminal because I think it's
cool.
You can use whatever makes you happy.
But I want to show you the command line because
I think it's important.
My opinion how to know how to drive a manual
transmission car manual stick car.
There's automatic shift cars. There's ubers.
But if you're going to drive a car.
It's nice to know how to change the engine you
fix the engine?
How to change the tires?
How to change the oil rather?
It's nice to know one layer underneath so while I
could do an entire demo in Visual Studio and never
show.
You the command line because I want you to really
understand what's happening.
I was going to spend a little bit of time
at the command line here to kind of kick off
your local event.
Now in the terminal of course in the new Windows
terminal.
I've got tabs so I can open up.
Lots of things I've got dos,
I've got PowerShell I've got aboon 2.
Talk about that in a little bit,
but if I go out here to dos.
And I say where.NET. Look where it is.
Cprogramfiles.NET.NET EXE in the past in the past.
Whereis.NET, well, it's in C windows.
Microsoft dot NET Framework. It lives in here.
Right that's the dot NET Framework that's the one that
ships with windows.
Now it's supported. It will be supported forever.
As long as Windows is supported you get updates through
Windows Update this is the original windows,
only framework. But.NET core.
Lives here in cprogramfiles.NET. And inside there,
I can have lots of different SDK's I can have.
Side by side Nets, which is really interesting now,
the one we're going to focusonrightnowis.NET core.
That's the only one that we really care about so
let's just go into an empty folder here.
And I'm going to say.NET new net is the command
line.
That's doing all the work here in the very first
time I run it.
It will run off some stuff and see look.
It says templates and then look at this short name
right here,
see this short name. I can say .NET new console .NET new unit test
or.NET new react application all of these are great.
Templates for you to make new projects lets do this .NET new.
Console.
And I'm going to say.
My console, I'm going to put it in a folder
called my console.
OK.
And let's go into the folder called my console.
See how simple this is it's just program dot CSS.
I'll open it in notepad to just show you how
basic it is.
Hello World, OK.
I think .NET run. Let's watch this and let's count.
1 2 3 4. That seems kind of slow you might say.
Start net slow. No run.
Actually does a restore? And to build a complete compiled.
Complete compile build.
Build and then it runs it,
but what it actually make let's go and look at
that bin folder.
There's the executable my console let's go and say.
My console.
Look how fast that is.
So I want to point out the .NET run is a great way
to run your application when you're developing it.
But then of course, now with .NET Core 3,
I'll just run that console.
.Net Core 3 creates this executable as a way
for you to run that application,
but the real app lives inside this console DLL.
In fact I can say .NET my console DLL and that.
That runs it so the code is inside here.
Now let's take that apart.
I'm going to take it apart with an application called
DnSpy.
Let's go and open that up.
Go to my desktop.
To the folder called demos.
Will grab that file? This is really interesting this is
a decompiler and you can notice here,
I can see the language.
The Intermediate language. Look at those 2 lines hello world
console dot right line.
I can look at them as C# now this
isn't.
The actual code it's just a presentation of the code
I can even see what hello world looks like in
visual basic.
What I've done is I've decompiled my application you see?
And I can look at it right there.
Notice that there's nothing that says Windows there.
There's nothing that says this version of the framework or
that version of the framework this is very.
Open generic code that runs anywhere.
I wonder if we could run that anywhere you think
let's try an experiment.
I'm going to leave windows and I'm going to go
over here to Aboon 2.
Now this is using WSL WSL is the windows subsystem
for Linux.
This is a real boon to machine running on windows.
Let's go to my desktop.
Where we put that stuff?
I think we put it in a folder called demos.
My console.
And it's in bin.
Net core app.
I want to say.NET here.
This is .NET 3 this is any ubuntu version of .NET.
This is a linux .NET in fact,
I can say where .NET or we think it switch on
Aboon 2 and it tells me it's not in C
program files.
It's in slash user slash bin .NET,
which is interesting, but can I go and run?
This DLL on Ubuntu.
I can look at that.
So we made the DLL in windows,
we compiled it. We're now running it with a different
net runner from Ubuntu.
I'm showing you this because I think it's important to
understand that you decide how portable your net application is
what's inside of this .NET application?
What's inside? What's inside? Is console,
writeline, so on. Ubuntu, it,
writes to that console on Windows it right so this
console.
If I'm going to go and put that somewhere else
and run it on a different platform.
However, they decided to go and make console.
Would dictate if it was possible.
So that means it .NET core is portable it's portable but.
Remember Remember before I said that it works with Windows
Forms that's kind of interesting.
Let's go back over to Windows.
And go into demos and say .NET new again.
And you can see here it says Winforms That's interesting
that's a very windows thing.
Let's go and say dot net new winforms my win
forms app.
I will go into my winforms app.
I'm gonna say dot net run.
And this will be a little bit slow for the
very first time going to compile everything and there's the
app.
This is a Windows Forms app.
OK let's go in. See in the bin folder.
Again, you can do all of this with Visual Studio,
but I want to show you how to do it
from the command line so that you know how to
fix things if they if they go wrong,
so you see how fast that is so nice that
is.
Now. This is a Windows app.
A Windows Forms app with the.NET core runtime inside so
the engine.
The heart of this application is .NET core runtime.
Let's see if we can prove that I'm going to
go and say process Explorer.
This is a great tool that let's you see inside
inside the process.
So let's run process. Explorer real quick and will put
this application over here and then process Explorer is going
to pop up.
And I'm going to look inside.
This application.
We called it my winforms app.
Let's right click on that and say properties.
And look inside.
You see the core CLR the core common language runtime.
That's really interesting so we ran our winforms app.
It's being executed with .NET core,
but look at this. It's using Windows functions so it's
OK to make a .NET application that runs for Windows using .NET
core remember earlier I held up a Raspberry Pi.
I can writea.NET core application that runs on the Raspberry
Pi.
They could say hello world,
it could talk to the console you can talk to
the keyboard.
But as soon as I do something that is Raspberry
Pi's specific if I talk to the GP-
IO pins that general purpose.
I opens now it's a Raspberry Pi app.
That doesn't change how .NET behaves it's just making the point
that if I make a call to a native API
or a hardware.
API now that application isn't portable anymore.
And that's OK because I'm writing a Raspberry Pi app
or a watch app.
Not every app automatically becomes cross platform,
so in this case, we have a Windows Forms app.
That is now specific to Windows.
If I go and look at that application.
And it's code.
You can see that it actually brings in.
System dot windows dot forms uses a new get package
and it runs that form.
This means that you'll be able to take your existing
dot NET Framework applications your full framework applications that run
on windows today?
They might be a little bit older,
perhaps you made. The application yesterday.
You can go and change that from being .NET
Framework. To .NET core you're basically taking your car and you're
swapping the engine out and put in a new faster
cooler engine inside but it's still your car?
Does that make sense it's pretty cool stuff?
So I want to point that out here?
My application ran on Aboon 2 and it also ran
on windows,
but I made a Windows specific application that runs only
but you can write anything with net core.
As at the engine level that's pretty cool stuff now
in the future.
In the future, we're going to try to take these
and combine them.
I'll do that again. The dot NET Framework over here
on windows.
Mono in Xamarin. Mono was open source Xamarin Powers Android
and iPhone applications .NET core is cross platform.
We're going to kind of combine those in the future
and call it .NET 5 and that's going to be basically
one net for all things that's going to be pretty
cool. That's in the future.
But.
Currently here's what the schedule looks like we just released .NET
core 3 that's out today.
Later this year in november.NET Core 3.1 will be out
and it's what's called an LTS release that's a long
term support?
Version of gotten can be supported for years and then
here's the cool part.
Every other year, you're going to get a new long
term support version,
so if you want the new fresh stuff.
You can get those on the even numbered years and
if you want a long term support version,
then you can go and get that.
The other thing I want to show you is the .NET.
Web page this is the main website for .NET.
I want to remind you that you click download and
you can get dot net for Windows for Linux for
Mac for Docker.
And then we made a bunch of videos for you.
We're going to translate these into local languages and try
to have captions for those languages.
But what we have here are about 80 videos to
teach people see this is a 19 part series on
see we've got an 8 part.
Series on .NET Core 13 part series on asp.NET core and we
also talk about Xamarin and Docker machine learning.
Apache spark all of these videos are free and you
can find them if you just goto .NET videos.
So I hope that gives you a sense of what's
going on in the dot net community right now and
I think it's really great that you are are celebrating
I hope you have a great day.
Bye.